Guide to the Harold E. Goettler Collection 1909-1968
University of Chicago Library
Goettler, Harold E. Collection
1909-1968
6.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Harold E. Goettler was a University of Chicago graduate (1914) who joined the United States Air Service in 1917. Goettler was killed in the line of duty during World War I, while flying supply runs to Allied troops trapped by Germans in the Argonne Forest. This collection contains memorabilia of Goettler's days as a student, including an exceptionally large and elaborate scrapbook representing his academic, athletic and social activities at University of Chicago. Also included are memorabilia from his time in the Air Service.
Information on Use
Access
Open for research. No restrictions
Biographical Note
Harold E. Goettler was a University of Chicago graduate (1914) who joined the United States Air Service in 1917. Goettler was killed in the line of duty during World War I, while flying supply runs to Allied troops trapped by Germans in the Argonne Forest (the infamous "Lost Batallion"). In recognition for his service, 1st Lt. Harold E. Goettler was posthumously awarded the Medal of Honor, one of only four U.S. airmen to receive that distinction.
Scope Note
This collection contains memorabilia of Goettler's days as a student, including an exceptionally large and elaborate scrapbook representing his academic, athletic and social activities at University of Chicago. Also included are memorabilia from his time in the Air Service, including copies of his diaries and photos, the originals of which are located at the U.S. Air Force Museum at Wright Patterson Air Force Base, Ohio.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
University of Chicago. Student Ephemera. Collection
Subject Headings
Goettler, Harold E.; University of Chicago -- Students; World War, 1914-1918; Scrapbooks
INVENTORY
- Harold E. Goettler, memorial publication, photocopy, 1968 (Box 1)
- Owl and Serpent Society, second annual letter, 1914 (Box 1)
- Red White, Vol. XI No. 5, 1909 (Box 1)
- "In Memory of Members of the University of Chicago Fallen in the War," program, 1919 (Box 1)
- 83rd and 90th Convocations at the University of Chicago, programs,1912-1914 (Box 1)
- The Delta Kappa Epsilon Quarterly, Vol. 39 No. 2, 1921 (Box 1)
- William Rainey Harper Memorial Library, dedication publication,1912 (Box 1)
- University of Chicago Magazine, two issues,1918-1923 (Box 1)
- Photocopy of football photograph, circa 1910-1914 (Box 1)
- Photographs of military service, 1917-1918 (Box 1)
- Certificate of Completion of a Major Course from the University of Chicago Extension Division, 1912 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook covers and binding, circa 1910 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook signatures 1-3, 1910-1913 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook signatures 4-5, 1910-1915 (Box 3)
- The Highest Possible Courage, reproduction of National Guard painting, mid-20th century (Box 3)
- United States Army, reproduction of memorial certificate, 1918 (Box 3)
- Congressional Medal of Honor for Valor, reproduction of certificate (Box 3)
- Notary public certificate, 1916 (Box 3)
- High school and college diplomas, 1909-1914 (Box 4)
- Harold H. Swift and Edna Goettler, correspondence and obituary, 1959 (Box 4)